this video is sponsored by hook theory
how much do i have to practice is there
any question more universal to learning
anything
whether it's a thing you want to learn
for yourself or learning that's been
thrust upon you you've probably asked
yourself how much do i have to practice
it sounds simple but it actually raises
a number of questions the first is how
much do you have to practice to what
what are your goals do you want to be
really good or just not embarrassingly
bad what does success look like to you
are you trying to be the absolute best
you can be or are you just trying to get
your teacher or your parents to stop
harassing you depending on your needs
you might have to practice quite a lot
over quite a long time or maybe you can
get by on a great deal less
everyone is different and there are so
many different factors that affect
talent skill and ability some of which
you can't really change but others you
might be able to work on regardless it
can be difficult to find objective
truths about these things many teachers
just say practice as much as possible or
practice x number of times per week
without really helping the student think
through how frequency of practice might
affect outcomes some people will just
trust their teacher and follow their
advice but others may need a bit more
convincing so let's start by looking at
how many times you could practice per
week and see what feels best for you
first off you could practice zero days
per week but i'm sure we can all agree
this is the worst choice think of all
the things you didn't practice this week
did any of them improve no no big
surprise there things don't tend to
improve with zero practice so we should
probably skip right ahead to practicing
at least one day per week
now something is better than nothing by
quite a lot actually but it can be
really hard to make habits stick or even
remember what you've learned when you're
spacing out your practice sessions so
much in the long term you're just not
racking up that many days so you'll have
to temper your expectations about your
progress but what if you double it to
two times per week maybe you try for a
practice session on the weekend and once
through the week it's not spectacular
but it's literally twice as good as once
a week you probably shouldn't expect
your progress to be terribly quick
because you're still taking a lot of
days off but if you're achieving your
goals maybe that's enough if you're not
achieving your goals you might want to
bump it up to 3 days a week which is
really pretty decent maybe you practice
once on the weekend and a couple of
times through the week if you're
practicing smart and being efficient
with your time you'll slowly get better
and the ratio of practice days to
non-practice days doesn't look so bad
anymore the only problem is you're still
spending more days not practicing than
practicing but that all changes if you
can just get to four days per week now
you're practicing more days than you're
not and sometimes two or three days in a
row this is the point where you can
count on making steady progress
of course five days a week is even
better habits form quickly when you're
practicing most days because you're only
taking a couple of days off each week
and your practice journal is filled with
streaks you're going to build muscle
memory and all the knowledge and skills
you acquire will give you an intuitive
understanding of your craft six days of
practice a week is fantastic because
you're only taking one day off and
you're likely making a conscious
decision to not practice on that one day
for personal or physical reasons and
this can be good because breaks are good
for the body and mind if you're only
taking one day off a week you're racking
up major practice time and you'll be
sure to reap the rewards
and clearly if you're able trying to
practice every day is the best way to
explore the limits of your abilities so
broadly speaking when considering all
the options practicing one or two times
a week is better than nothing but you
can probably expect progress to be slow
three days a week is not bad but four or
five times a week is so much better
because you're practicing more days than
you're not practicing and if you want to
find out just how good you can be at
something you've got to be practicing
close to every day
given these guidelines there are two
things to keep in mind first just
because you spend time on something
doesn't guarantee you'll actually
improve because quality of practice is
just as important as quantity if not
more so you can spend lots of time on
something but not make much progress if
you don't practice well i did a whole
separate video about using your time
efficiently called how to get better by
practicing less be sure to check it out
especially if you feel like you're
putting in the time but still not
improving it could be quality of
practice rather than quantity the other
thing is it's worth asking the question
what counts as practice as a music
teacher i often ask students how many
times they're practicing per week on
average and some will surprise me by
saying almost every day because their
progress really doesn't show it
sometimes it's bad practice habits but
often they'll go on to explain that they
have class three times a week and two
rehearsals so that's five times a week
but they never actually take the horn
out of the case at home and come on
that's just inflating numbers on a
technicality it almost reminds me of
when mitch hedberg said i like rice rice
is great when you're hungry and you want
to eat 2 000 to something
now there's no doubt that any time a
musician is spending time doing music
it's a good thing but just as all
musical activities are related and
sometimes overlap each one is also
unique and doesn't really substitute for
one another so the only thing that
counts as practice is practice
practice can include many different
activities in itself but fundamentally
to me the whole point of practice is
working on things that you need to work
on and that might be very different from
other people you play with so it's
important to have time together and work
on ensemble stuff but also time alone to
work on your own areas of weakness you
need to balance practicing as a group
and practicing as an individual and then
when you all return to practice as a
group you're all far stronger many other
fields are similar to music athletes
have to do drills with their team
scrimmage and have real playing
experience in games
but they also need to hit the gym train
and work on that thing they need to get
better at it doesn't matter if it's free
throws forehands or field goals if you
want to improve a skill you've got to
find time to practice it maybe hundreds
of times even skills like learning a
language which is going to require lots
of practical real life experience
speaking with and listening to other
people is also going to progress much
faster if you can find time to sit down
and work on new vocabulary and phrases
study grammar and sentence structure and
read books and magazines multiple
avenues of learning can be very
beneficial so feel free to adapt your
practice schedule to the needs of your
particular craft but be honest with
yourself about what you need to work on
and if you're actually spending enough
time on it
if your craft happens to be music you
need to look at some of the incredible
products from this video's sponsor hook
theory chord crush teaches you to hear
chord progressions by ear using real
songs and their interactive books help
you learn and practice music theory but
i think one of their coolest products is
called hook pad which helps songwriters
create beautiful chord progressions and
melodies even if you don't have much
music theory or the ability to chord
well on piano or guitar songwriting is
much more practice based than most
people think you need to write often and
get used to making choices every song
you write will make you better and hook
pad makes it so much easier head to hook
theory dot com slash brad harrison for
exclusive discounts on chord crush hook
pad and their music theory books thanks
so much to hook theory for sponsoring
this video
now the other question that's implied by
how much should i practice is how long
should a practice session be just like
how many days a week you should practice
it depends on your age experience and
goals little kids might only have the
ability to focus for 10 or 15 minutes
and you can't really expect them to do
much more than that and beginners of any
age might have limits that aren't much
longer because new things are hard and
they may be building the physical
endurance and mental focus to practice
longer but for most teens and adults i
think a good session length to aim for
is about 30 minutes it's not too long
and not too short it gives you enough
time to get your gear and get settled do
a warm-up run some drills and technique
and dig into whatever the project of the
day is
however long your practice session is
it's good to keep in mind that it takes
most people a few minutes to warm up so
they feel good and sound good get into
the flow of things and wake up the right
part of their brain so they can get good
work done probably at least 10 minutes
or so in a short practice session that
takes up a decent amount of your time
and that's fine that's just how it works
but if you can go a little bit longer
you'll probably find the extra time goes
further than you might expect your total
practice time only increases a bit but
your productive time increases faster
because your warm up usually stays about
the same
also realize that it's important to
strike a balance between how long a
practice session is and how often you
practice practicing for two hours is
great but it's not ideal if you only do
that once a week it's probably better to
break that time into four 30-minute
sessions you'll build strength endurance
and habits much faster that way
finally some people want to practice but
have trouble finding the time and
there's no doubt we're all busy you may
have demands from school work family or
friends or obligations to teams clubs or
other organizations
the first thing to think about is be
careful about how many obligations you
choose to take on it's easy to say yes
to everything and it's good to try to do
a lot of things to a point because you
have to be careful not to spread
yourself too thin
i don't think being constantly stressed
and exhausted is the badge of honor some
people seem to think it is no matter
what you decide to focus on keep in mind
if you only practice when you find
yourself with nothing else to do it's
just never going to happen if you really
want to find time to practice make it a
priority find time in your schedule and
slot it in treat it like an appointment
or homework because it's not going to
happen on its own and if you happen to
be very serious about becoming the best
you can be you might consider all these
options to get multiple sessions
totaling a few hours each day that may
be unthinkable for some people but
there's just so many different things to
practice and if you're considering
making this skill set a part of your
career path a few hours of daily
practice is the kind of time commitment
that's generally necessary but for most
people who want to improve but aren't
necessarily concerned with becoming an
absolute world-class elite performer 30
minutes or so three to five times a week
is a really decent achievable goal
progress might not be obvious within
days or even weeks but the hours really
pile up after just a few months if
you've got decent practice habits you're
going to see improvement over time and
regardless of your goals you want to
minimize distractions while practicing
because even small disruptions can
really interrupt flow and impede
progress especially when practice time
is at a premium so don't be shy about
asking your friends or family to respect
your practice time they'll surely
understand if you explain it to them
gently and they'll probably respect your
dedication too then put your phone on do
not disturb and get to work be sure to
like comment share and subscribe and hit
that bell thing too and check my channel
for lots of videos on practice and music
theory thanks for watching
you